Let’s try an uppercase Y, as in many programming
languages, uppercase gets us a bigger format. I
will rerun the code, and we have the format
we want for the date. For time, the thinking
needs to be a little different. Most, but not
all time formats use uppercase letters. I will
add a space to the formatted date and then type
percent capital H colon percent capital M. I will
rerun the code and the time worked. Note that H
represents 24-hour time. An uppercase I represents
12 hour time, in which case you would also need
a percent lowercase P to represent AM or PM,
as I am doing here. At times, you may want the day
of the week to display. Many programming languages
have a built-in weekday function. Let’s see if
Python does. I will add a print statement to line
4 to indicate the day of the week and then the
current_time, and I will add the weekday method,
with parentheses, to the statement. In running
this code, we see a number for the weekday,
with Monday being 0, Tuesday being 1, and so
forth. In many cases, one would think we need an
if statement to parse out this number and return
a day. Oh, but wait. The strftime method has a
symbol we can use to get the weekday. I will
copy the print statement on line 4 to line 5,
change the method used to strftime, and put
%uppercase A in the parentheses inside of
quotes. I will then rerun the code, and we see
the day of the week perfectly. One of the vital
programming tenets to learn about any language
is retrieving the current date and then knowing
how to format a date. These skills allow one
to display dates when needed and use dates in
calculations when required, such as for figuring
out how long a game took or, outside of gaming,
when tasks are due or the time it took to
complete a job or tasks within that job.